Hydrocarbons contain only carbon and hydrogen.
They come mainly from petroleum, natural gas, and coal.
They give LPG, CNG, petrol, diesel, and kerosene,
and make polymers, solvents, dyes, and drugs.
Classify hydrocarbons by carbon-carbon bonding.
Saturated means only C-C single bonds.
Alkanes are open-chain cycloalkanes.
Rings on saturated means double or triple bonds.
Alkenes contain C-C double bonds.
Alkynes contain C-C triple bonds.
Aromatic compounds carry delocalized pi electrons.
Benzene, toluene, and naphthalene are examples.
Open-chain alkanes follow CNH2 and plus 2sp3.
Carbon tetrahedral-shaped bond angle near 109.5.
C-C single bonds allow free rotation.
Nonpolar chains, weak van der Waals force,
water-insoluble, soluble in nonpolar solvent substitution.
Combustion cracking confirmations, these are alkane revision keys.
Every alkane carbon is sp3 hybridized.
C-C bond is about 1.54 picometers.
C-H bond is about 1.12 picometers.
Chain isomerism gives different skeletons.
C4H10 gives n-butane and isovutane.
C6H14 has 5 isomers.
Isomer count rises with carbon number.
For naming, choose the longest chain number to give substituents the lowest numbers.
Alkyl groups are CNH2 and plus 1, made when 1 hydrogen leaves an alkane.
Follow IUPAC rules in the name.
Use alphabetical order for substituents.
Alkanes formed by hydrogenation of alkanes or alkynes.
With platinum, palladium, or nickel.
Alkyl halides reduced with zinc and HCl.
Or a couple in words reaction with sodium.
Carboxylic acids decarboxylate with soda lime.
Calvae electrolysis uses sodium carboxylates.
Alkanes follow CNH2 and plus 2.
Sp3 carbon tetrahedral shape.
Bond angle near 109.5.
C-C-C single bonds allow free rotation.
Nonpolar chains weak van der Waals force.
Water insoluble soluble in nonpolar solvent substitution.
Combustion cracking conformations.
These are alkane revision keys.
C1 to C4 are gases.
C5 to C17 are liquids.
C18 and higher are solids.
Boiling point rises with molecular mass.
Branching lowers boiling point because surface contact becomes less.
Free radical substitution gives halogenation under ultraviolet light.
Complete combustion gives carbon dioxide.
Water and heat when oxygen is enough.
Incomplete combustion produces carbon monoxide or soot.
Controlled oxidation gives alcohols, aldehydes, acids.
Isomerization makes branched chains.
Aromatization gives aromatic compounds.
Methane plus steam gives CO and 3H2.
H2 for industrial hydrogen production.
Pyrolysis or cracking breaks large hydrocarbons into smaller alkanes and alkenes.
Rotation about C-C single bonds gives conformational isomerism.
And ethane eclipsed hydrogens align higher energy.
Staggered is lower and more stable.
Open chain alkanes follow C and H2 and plus 2sp3.
Carbon tetrahedral shape.
Newman and Sawhorse show conformers.
Eclipsed and staggered in rotation.
About 12.5 kilojoules per mole is the ethane energy barrier.
Formula naming substitution and conformations.
Complete the alkane revision track.
Revise alkanes by structure, isomerism, naming, preparation, properties and reactions.